<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the King and Queen, a proclamation for the careful custody and well ordering of the new river brought from Chadwell and Amwell to the north parts of the city of London</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1689-1694 : William and Mary)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38096</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17187503</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17187503</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106124</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106124)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1624:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the King and Queen, a proclamation for the careful custody and well ordering of the new river brought from Chadwell and Amwell to the north parts of the city of London</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1689-1694 : William and Mary)</author>
                  <author>Mary II, Queen of England, 1662-1694.</author>
                  <author>William III, King of England, 1650-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2] leaves.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Bill and Thomas Newcomb ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Broadside in [2] leaves.</note>
                  <note>"Given at our court at Hampton  Court the six and twentieth day of September, 1689.. In the first year of our reign"--Leaf [2]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rivers --  England --  Regulation.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:106124:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>monogram of 'W' (William) superimposed on 'M' (Mary)</figDesc>
                     </figure> RR</head>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QUI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>By the King and Queen, A PROCLAMATION For the careful Cuſtody and well Ordering of the New River brought from <hi>Chadwell</hi> and <hi>Amwell</hi> to the North Parts of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>William R.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas by Authority of two ſeveral Acts of Parliament Made and Ordained in the Third and Fourth Years of the Reign of King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, Our Royal Anceſtor of Bleſſed Memory, the River now running from <hi>Chadwell</hi> and <hi>Amwell</hi> in Our County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> to the North Parts of Our City of <hi>London,</hi> was at the great Charge of the ſaid King, and other the Vndertakers, happily made and finiſhed; Since which time the Water thereof is diſperſed by Pipes and Branches through the ſeveral Streéts and Places of Our ſaid City, and the Liberties and Suburbs of the ſame, and elſewhere, to the Benefit and Eaſe of Our Subjects there Inhabiting, as well for the cleaning and ſweet keéping of them in the times of Infection, as the preſervation and ſafety of the Houſes and Buildings, Goods and Riches therein, from the fearful danger of Fire caſually happening; And ſuch was the Care and Providence of His ſaid Majeſty King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, that the Water in any place in the courſe thereof, ſhould not at any time be troubled or corrupted (whereby the Health or Lives of the People might ſuffer or be endangered) that by His Letters Patents of Incorporation, dated the One and twentieth day of <hi>June,</hi> in the Seventeénth Year of His Reign over this Our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> he Created and Erected a Governour and Company, ſucceſſively to Regulate, and carefully to Overſee all things appertaining to the ſaid River; And ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſtrict Orders and Commands were Made and Given by the ſaid late King, for preſervation of the ſaid River, and preventing of ſuch things as might be prejudicial thereunto; Notwithſtanding which, the preſent Governour and Company have Repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto Vs, That great Abuſes are daily committed: We therefore taking into Our Princely Conſideration, That the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:106124:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the ſaid River is of great and eſpecial Conſequence, are Graciouſly pleaſed by this Our Royal Proclamation (with the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Our Privy Council) ſtraitly to Charge and Command, That all and every the Grants, Clauſes and Reſtrictions in the ſaid Acts of Parliament, Letters Patents, and in all other Letters Patents, Orders and Proclamations concerning the ſaid Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Enacted, Made, Eſtabliſhed, Granted or Confirmed, be from time to time carefully obeyed, obſerved and performed; And We do hereby ſtrictly prohibit and forbid all and ſingular the Inhabitants of Our City of <hi>London,</hi> the Suburbs and Liberties thereof, Our City of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and alſo the Inhabitants of Our ſeveral Counties of <hi>Middleſex</hi> and <hi>Hertford,</hi> and likewiſe all the Plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, Paviers, and other Artificers whomſoever, and every of them, That they nor any of them, do or ſhall preſume at any time or times hereafter, without the privity, permiſſion and allowance of the Governour and Company aforeſaid for the time being, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termeddle with the ſaid Works, or any of the Pipes or Branches thereof, or to convey or derive any Pipe or Branch, Pipes or Branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of the ſaid Water, into their, or any of their Houſes, or other Places, nor ſhall fetch or carry the Water out of the ſaid River, the Pipes or Branches thereof, or otherwiſe hinder, waſte or conſume, diſturb, infect, abuſe or corrupt the ſame River, by ſetting up of Grates, overflowing of Grounds, making of Trenches or Drains, filling of Ponds, Fiſhing, Watering of Cattel, keéping of Geéſe or Ducks thereupon, caſting of Carrion thereinto, Waſhing themſelves therein, or by doing or permitting any Miſuſance, Annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Let, Stoppage or Prejudice whatſoever, to the Stream of Our ſaid River in any part of the Currant thereof, nor ſhall cut, ſpoil, take a way or deſtroy any of the Branches, Bridges, Wharfs, Poſts, Rails, Banks, Mounds or Fences to the ſaid River in any wiſe belonging or appertaining, or therewith enjoyed, or lying near or behooveful to the ſame; And that the ſaid Governour and Company, their Officers and Servants ſhall have free liberty in the day-time, in the preſence of a Conſtable, to Search any Houſe, Yard or Back-ſide, where they ſhall ſuſpect any Branch or Branches are laid contrary to their knowledge, upon Pain of Our High Diſpleaſure, and of ſuch Pains, Penalties and Puniſhments, as by the Law and Statutes of this Kingdom, or Our Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Royal, can and may be inflicted upon the Offenders for Contempt of Our Royal Will and Pleaſure herein Declared. And We do hereby ſtrictly Charge and Command all Mayors, Iuſtices of the Peace, Commiſſioners of Sewers, Sheriffs, Bailiffs, Conſtables, Headboroughs, and all other Our Officers, Miniſters and Subjects within Our ſaid Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> the Suburbs and Liberties thereof, Our Counties of <hi>Middleſex</hi> and <hi>Hertford,</hi> whom the ſame ſhall or may concern, That they and every of them hereafter be vigilant and circumſpect, that Our Royal Will and Pleaſure herein Declared, be from time to time effectually obſerved; And that they and every of them in their ſeveral Offices and Places reſpectively, without Excuſe or Delay, be upon all Occaſions Aiding and Aſſiſting to the ſaid Governour and Company, their Officers and Miniſters, in the ſtrict Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervance and Execution of all and ſingular the Powers and Authorities, Limitations and Reſtraints herein before mentioned, and in the Grants and Prohibitions aforeſaid contained, according to the true intent and meaning of theſe Preſents, when they ſhall be thereunto required by them or any of them, as they and every of them tender Our Pleaſure, and will anſwer the contrary at their Perils.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at Our Court at <hi>Hampton-Court</hi> the Six and twentieth Day of <date>
                     <hi>September,</hi> 1689. In the Firſt Year of Our Reign.</date>
               </dateline>
               <lb/>
God ſave the King and Queen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Charles Bill</hi> and <hi>Thomas Newcomb,</hi> Printers to the King and Queens moſt Excellent Majeſties. 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
